[Music]
thank you
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask Abhijit show it is a pleasure and a
privilege to be amongst you all this
fine evening over here and I hope you're
all doing very very well
before I begin to greet you let me just
uh inform you in case you're not aware
that we now have a Discord Channel and
we also have a telegram uh channel so
you can find the links in the
description below and I would like to
invite you all to join the Discord
server and participate in divisions in
discussions Etc over there and hopefully
once we have sufficient numbers of
people I could even do a private ask a
visit show on Discord possibly
eventually once we have sufficient
numbers and similarly on telegram the
advantage of joining the telegram
channel is that you will be always
notified of when a new video comes out
so uh please consider joining the
Discord channel in the telegram Channel
as well uh so yeah so that's what I
wanted to inform you beginning uh in the
in the very beginning
now let's see who all is there on the
live chat I can see vaishnavi Japan
Arrow 14 God of s adarsh z l n l x 27
soumya Dixit Sumit Agarwal glassy Sky
sumeda Amit gosan feminist Slayer ansh
Sharma plush bar no problem
Aryan Sharma Pawan Suraj mukund
Siddharth Dr suryakandagar charvaka
Karthik pundir Tejas history for you
Kumari
uh
Mahesh arjit Arijit samrat Aditi Nishant
pratik Venus
Mohan Roy Dinesh Chandra
Sherlock Holmes Sagar Durga thinking
Flex
and everybody else Dr Jason Supremacy
Ali Raza Ansari shahiden
veg chicken and everybody else okay okay
okay let me let me stop that it's
already four minutes in otherwise I'll
be able I'll be Mateo Perez hello so
I'll be otherwise you know greeting you
all until then you know the end of this
session so let's let's stop the
greetings now I greet you all
collectively thank you so much now let's
get into the questions
where shall We Begin so let's let's get
going ask me your questions and let's
take some interesting questions maybe
some fun questions I like fun I like to
laugh I like to be happy we often get
very serious questions and things that
sometimes kind of make me a little bit
angry at times
yeah I I always say don't I that we
should keep emotions aside well it
doesn't mean that emotions don't exist
emotions do exist but when we make
decisions we have to keep emotions aside
and think logically and clinically
anyhow let's take uh some questions
let us begin with Tejas they just says
what are your views on Kumari kandam do
you think it existed well the the
question of Kumari kandam has been
around for quite some time and
apparently uh in certain texts uh Tamil
texts it it is written that there used
to be a much uh larger area that was uh
inhabited by by people in ancient times
and it was called Kumari kundam
uh and so now people have constructed uh
you know
theories or hypothesis out of this uh
out of this textual evidence that we
have and some people call it limuria or
something some people just call it
Kumari kandam and the claim is that
there was a massive enormous continent
South of uh the southern part of India
in the Indian Ocean that was called
Kumari kandam well I would invite you
all to take a look at undersea undersea
uh maps of the Indian Ocean we clearly
we have very detailed and very clear
maps of the uh bottom
of the Indian Ocean and the entire world
essentially
and you can clearly see the tracks left
behind by the tectonic movement of the
Indian subcontinent from Africa all the
way into Eurasia when it's slammed into
Eurasia you can see the tracks left
behind you know you can see the ridges
and tracks so it's clear that this this
event happened of the Indian
subcontinent moving away from Africa
because of tectonic activity about 120
million years ago and slamming into the
Eurasian uh continent about 50 40
million years ago that's when it began
but there is no evidence of a sunken
continent that was once above the ocean
there is absolutely no evidence
whatsoever of that the uh evidence the
data is unambiguous there was no such
hidden or sunken continent that would
have once been above the surface of the
ocean in maybe during the last glacial
uh minimum when uh maybe 12 000 or so
years ago when the sea levels were about
120 or so meters below where they are
today so there is no such continent but
there there we we do find evidence of
sunken cities
all across
all around the the geography of the
Indian subcontinent in the west we have
dwarka and the Gulf of khambat
archaeological complex which is the
network of uh submerged cities and in
the South also you know in the east of
of the coast of Tamil Nadu you do we do
find uh
only recently the archaeologists uh I
think in February or January or
somewhere around that time they
discovered a large submerged City
uh Clues to present-day puducherry
pondicherry
it's approximately at least a hundred
square kilometers the site that's large
that's very large and it's it's about 80
or 100 meters below the sea so that's
that corresponds to a time period of at
least eight to ten thousand years before
today and it's being speculated right
now we don't know for sure but it could
be the lost city of
[Music]
the sangam era so it's clear
that Indian civilization whether it's a
it's it's at least 10 000 years old if
not much older than that right and uh
that that dates back to the time the
last ice age was very much in force so
the Contours of the Indian subcontinent
which were much larger than what they
are today Sri Lanka was connected was
part of the Indian subcontinent it was
not a separate Island at that time about
12 15 17 000 years before today Sri
Lanka was very much part of the Indian
subcontinent it was just one single land
mass
so yes
that if we want to interpret that as the
lost continent or the Lost land then
it's very much that but there is no
large enormous submerged continent that
will someday emerge that's that's not
the case Okay so uh yeah that is the
answer I don't think it existed because
I have seen the data there is no
evidence that such a large submerged
continent ever existed
ripe
so my point is that we have to look at
evidence we have to look at evidence and
base our understanding of the world on
the hard evidence archaeological
evidence empirical evidence right and
there is no evidence of that and it's
not going to appear in the future new
evidence of a lost continent it's not
going to happen
okay
next next next next next
Nishant Duhan says is it true that a not
too distant Supernova explosion can
cause an Ice Age on Earth
um not too distant Supernova explosion
so let's let's think of the closest star
that we have which is the Alpha Centauri
Proxima Centauri system which is about
four point something light years away
from Earth that's a reasonably small
star it's it's not going to go supernova
uh so let's say we hypothetically
theoretically hypothetically that we
have a super node that goes off about 10
years 10 light years away from Earth so
that's going to go give off a shock wave
and all that uh it could certainly uh
some of that ejected material over time
could make its way to the solar system I
don't see it having a very large impact
on the solar system
um because by the time it reaches the
solar system the outer Contours the
outer areas of the solar system it would
have kind of dissipated and the shock
won't be that much it's gonna be mostly
gas only gas and some dust so uh no
so I don't see that happening we do have
other uh astrophysical objects like
quasars for instance
uh
and gamma ray bursts so those are very
intense and very tightly collimated
beams of extremely energetic radiation
so if one of that
uh phenomena impacts the earth I mean if
in case this if phenomenon happens and
the beam is aimed right at the Earth it
can strip away the ozone layer and the
outer layers of the atmosphere and and
you know expose us to solar radiation
cosmic rays and all that and cause
complete Devastation on the planet and
it's possible such things may have
happened in the past it's a possibility
that one of the the Earth has gone
through multiple waves of mass
extinctions over the past four and a
half let's say 3.7 billion years years
ever since life is known to have emerged
so it I'm sure I don't remember I don't
remember which mass extinction event it
was but one of these mass extinction
events is hypothesized as having
possibly perhaps been caused by you know
again one of these events
so
a supernova which may happen maybe 10 20
light years away won't really affect us
too much unless it's a very large
Supernova like for instance a star like
Beetlejuice but we don't have any such
star in our neighborhood so we're we're
safe
okay
light right right let's see something
else
um devansh Desai says I want my friends
to believe that our education system is
not that useful in our history is Gandhi
were not good and as they are glorified
in books what to do
well you can bring a camel to water but
you can't make the camel drink the water
right so listen the the point is this uh
you should not spend too much time and
effort and energy trying to convince
people of what they don't want to
believe you can show them the evidence
that you have and give them the choice
of whether they want to actually use
their intelligence and and try to
understand the evidence or whether they
just want to go along with the
conditioning that is that the education
system gives us most people don't want
to make the effort maybe because it's
too too hard it's too difficult thinking
is is hard
most people don't like to think it hurts
I think the brain you know so most
people just want to be told what to
think and they will think
they don't want to learn how to think
because that's a difficult process
so they we go through the education
system it takes us like years and years
from the time we are essentially three
years old and until we are past 20 and
we are repeatedly conditioned mentally
conditioned mentally programmed
brainwashed and we are told what to
think that's how the education system is
so most of us are comfortable with that
very few people actually want to uh you
know consider new ideas and new
information and possibly rethink the way
they've been
looking at the world that's very rare so
I would say devansh don't spend too much
time and effort and energy trying to
convince people if they want to you can
you can give them the information and
whatever knowledge understanding you
have and let them decide
that's what I would say it's really hard
to convince people especially those who
don't want to be convinced all right
all right all right all right
um
right
says could you elaborate why Italy is
Banning English at the government level
initially will workism be the downfall
of the West
um these are two separate uh things
maybe there may be some connection
between them I yeah why do I think Italy
is Banning English see
for the past several hundred years the
world has been ruled and controlled by
the Anglo-Saxon Saxon Empire the
English-speaking uh
people they have been ruling the world
and after 1945 with the end of the
second world war Europe was essentially
occupied by by the Anglo-Saxon Saxon
Empire it's actually the U.S with the
uks of assault and Italy and Germany
came under permanent military occupation
which still continues most people don't
see it because that's not what we are
taught but it is the case and so the
same happened to Japan after after
Hiroshima and Nagasaki
so now that so this situation still
continues there are U.S military bases
on Italian soil
which are considered to be jointly
operated bases and if you look at the
Wikipedia article it will say that the
Italian government has the right to any
time as the Americans to leave yeah nice
to nice to know that thank you very much
so now that now the world is changing
significantly in the 2020s we are
witnessing a very rapid realignment of
of geopolitical of the geopolitical
chess board and the world can visibly
see that the influence of the US is
decreasing not the power as such but the
influence is certainly decreasing and
with this decreased influence there will
be this this this uh Trend or this
desire among the occupied Nations to
kind of start the process of breaking
free from the shackles of the
Anglo-Saxon Empire
and uh yeah so that is part of I mean
that's and so this uh move by the
Italian government to start uh
start you know phasing English out
is most likely a step in that direction
Italy and India have reset the ties very
significantly with the recent visit of
Madame Georgia Maloney to India she was
given a very warm warm welcome she had a
great time in India she was given the
greatest of respect and uh
so uh India and Italy seem to be
resetting their ties and there's going
to be you know after after many many
many many years and Decades of not very
good relations but now things are on a
different track and things are going
well
so all these nations in Europe
especially Western Europe are now kind
of looking eastwards and they know that
they can't really trust China China is a
dangerous Nation China doesn't China
seeks to replace the U.S or the
Anglo-Saxon Empire and create a Chinese
Empire over the world right so China is
a dangerous Nation from the perspective
but India is not seen as a threatening
Nation India is it that powerful yet of
course first of all yeah when India in
20 years maybe reaches where China is
today maybe the world may perhaps
you know ask itself what kind of a power
is in India is India you know but at
this point it's about cooperation
collaboration and all that's obviously
that uh so yes uh Italy maybe that's why
Italy is trying to phase
English out at certain levels
um will work isn't with the downfall of
the West yes
for whatever reason the the powers that
be in the West
have turned on their own people they're
destroying their own Society they're
destroying
the structure the foundations of society
and culture
and you see these Cycles you know in in
in in Judean history
you have the concept of Sodom and
Gomorrah
which were two cities where which were
totally degenerate degeneracy of of all
kinds over there you know whatever you
traditionally hold as good was was was
uh kind of uh
uh abused over there and whatever you've
traditionally seen as as
bad or evil was celebrated in Sodom and
Gomorrah and then eventually you're the
wrath of God the biblical God that
destroyed these two cities
so that's that's that's a tale or or a
myth it's part of the mythology we have
no not seen any evidence of these two
cities ever existing but yeah that's
part of the uh mythology in the Judean
world and then obviously we have the
example of the Roman Empire which
descended into all kinds of excess and
degeneracy
uh for a couple of centuries while it
was declining declining and today an
Empire doesn't decline over a couple of
centuries today we have technology which
accelerates everything it's an
accelerant
right techno technology is a catalyst
for acceleration of change so today an
empire disintegrates in 20 30 years
and
what we call vocism was earlier called
social justice Warrior is Warrior
Behavior sjw Behavior now it's called
vocism you can call it whatever you want
but they are eating up their own culture
and traditions and they're destroying
the society that's what we're witnessing
so we and they're trying to export it to
other countries including in India so as
we know lots of media channels I'm not
saying all but many possibly potentially
allegedly
or maybe factually are funded by by
outside forces
including from the West
and obviously they will obviously if
they are on their payroll they will do
whatever these outside forces want them
to do so they will portray certain you
know they will try and import all of
this Behavior into India and try to
influence the hearts and minds of young
people especially
so it could not just be the downfall of
the West it could destroy India as well
you know so one has to be careful we
have to be careful here in India
okay
says as the US dollar influences
declining globally so in the future
could repeat could the rupee become
become a Global Currency can India how
can India make this happen you know a
couple of hundred years ago the rupee
was one of the dominant color currencies
in the world
or even in the 19th century even in the
20th century the century the rupee was
used as the currency in The crucial
states in the Middle East in the Gulf
region
they had their own Gulf rupee which was
an extension of the Indian rupee the
rupee was one of the main drivers of the
economy but after 1944 we had the
um what's it called
what's it called the name eludes me uh
the Bretton Woods the Britain Woods
system was was created and the US dollar
was adopted as the global Reserve
currency because the U.S essentially had
won the second world war and had the
world at its feet so that's what
happened and then this the West started
devaluing the Indian rupee some will
people will say abhijita is has no idea
of what he is saying it was the Indian
government that was devaluing the Indian
rupee well please remember what happened
in 1947 it was a transfer of power from
one set of crooks to another set of
crooks so it was Western agents that
come to power that came to power in
India in 1947.
and until very recently it was the same
people who were ruling India in their
own way and they were doing whatever was
well you know so we know that the the
economic policies Etc and other policies
were terrible for India
and you saw the devaluation gradual
devaluation of the Indian rupee over
time I think in the 1990s one dollar was
30 or so rupees roughly give or take
care and there something okay I don't
remember exactly what it is Google it if
you want
so around around the 1990s one dollar
was around roughly 25 30 rupees today is
around 80 rupees
there was a time when one dollar was one
rupee
you know so the West has exported its
inflation to India by using the Indian
rupee and so on So eventually what's
going to happen is that the Indian rupee
will indeed rise what India has to do is
to enter into bilateral and multilateral
agreements with other nations to use the
Indian rupee as a medium of exchange and
medium of trade and obviously this will
only work if India Rises economically
right now India is a 3.5 roughly
trillion dollar economy we have to first
reach the five trillion dollar Mark and
then the trend 10 trillion dollar Mark
to really matter in the world but people
can see the world can see the trajectory
that Indian the the Indian economy is
upon so uh so we are in good trip so
what India needs to do is to uh is to
keep growing its economic that's what
India has to do focus on the economy
keep growing the economy ensure there is
no major military conflict with other
nations for the next 20 years at least
10 years or hopefully 20 years by the
time we will be in a really good
position yeah so why now the first
question is why is the US dollar uh
influence declining globally because the
now the world
in the past 10 20 years has kind of seen
through what the US has done to the
world they always take this position of
moral superiority they talk about human
rights democracy they prefers today one
of the uh I forget the name of the
person on Twitter who who works for the
for Rand corporation which destroyed the
life and career of John Forbes Nash the
great mathematician and Economist so
that Corporation Grant corporation which
is the U.S Think Tank which is
affiliated with the defense
establishment one of their minions
was lecturing Vietnam on human rights
it's it's like Germany lecturing the
Jews about human rights that sort of
thing The Americans
we all know what they did in Vietnam
Untold horrific atrocities entire nation
they bombed millions of tons of you know
bombs on on the civilians of Vietnam not
just not just Vietnam Cambodia also Laos
also yeah
and agent orange that horrific chemical
that still causes genetic defects in
people that that's what they sprayed
liberally over the forests of Vietnam
Vietnam is still full of anti-personnel
and other mines people still die every
year because of that who did that
in all the massacres the Americans
Massacre and whatnot and they are
lecturing Vietnam on human rights today
it's it's like a global Cosmic joke
you know it's it's the epitome the the
the Pinnacle the zeniths of
shamelessness so the world has seen
through what the Americans truly are
you know they are nothing but a hard
hegemonic destructive power that seeks
to rule the world and they don't want
democracy or human rights anywhere
they're very happy to prop up
dictatorships all across Africa
they have they propped up the Saudi uh
Kingdom
which is not a democracy which doesn't
belong believe in human rights they
propped up this one family the family
the house of Saud
for decades and now that Muhammad bin
Salman is trying to actually liberalize
the country to a certain extent
they they are very much against him so
the world is seen through this you know
of course other powers are now emerging
that's the real reason why the influence
of the US dollar is declining the
Russians and the Chinese and possibly
certain other nations could come
together and create their own currency
and all that so these are the things
that are happening right now the 2020s
are gonna be a decade of great great
churn and realignment and by that time
2030 comes around it's going to be a
very different world in so many
different ways so uh that's the reason
why the U.S dollar is declining I mean
nations are trying to move making moves
to move away from the US dollar We're
not gonna see that happen
anytime very soon but by 2030 you could
see a very different world you know
economically in terms of global Reserve
currencies
all right
what are the questions
can quantum entanglement manipulate
human consciousness well that's that's
an open question quantum entanglement is
a phenomenon that we do kind of
understand much better now uh but we
don't understand human consciousness at
all
science doesn't even have a clear
definition or even a vague definition of
what Consciousness is consciousness is a
thing nobody can deny it it is a thing I
mean when we humans when we see
Consciousness we recognize it
immediately you see a cat we know that
cat is conscious we see a dog we know
the dog is conscious you see a crow
somewhere you know the crow is conscious
you see a snake that snake has a certain
level of consciousness
we see other people they're conscious so
we know Consciousness is
a phenomenon that exists in nature it's
but what is it do we have a definition
we don't have a neurological definition
of Consciousness we don't have a
chemical biological definition of
Consciousness and we don't have a
physical definition of Consciousness
what constitutes a physical system let's
say I give you a black box and it it has
a Consciousness within how do I Define
the parameters of that Consciousness and
what is consciousness is it an emergent
phenomenon that emerges out of complex
systems so the so the more complex a
system is the more conscious it is which
would imply that the entire universe has
even rocks and stones and trees and
plants and whatever has has some level
of Consciousness so we don't know
if it's an emergent phenomenon that
emerges out of complexity maybe
microscopic complexity then maybe the
quantum world could possibly uh
contribute to that or possibly give rise
to that now clearly we know that
Consciousness in human beings resides
here we know it is here we are all we we
perceive the world from here and we know
what happens when someone's brain is
damaged you know it impacts the
Consciousness so we know that the brain
is the seat of the Consciousness so it
seems like it it Consciousness is
something that resides in a physical
apparatus a very the human brain is the
most complex
thing machine whatever you want to call
it object known in the in the known
universe
so Consciousness perhaps emerges out of
complexity or maybe complexity attracts
Consciousness from somewhere we have no
idea
and we don't even know how quantum
entanglement would work in the human
brain the human brain is this big messy
wet object very complicated object
and does it have uh you know clearly at
the ultra microscopic level it's all
Quantum so how does it work so we don't
have the answers and one of the real
reasons is not because we don't
understand quantum entanglement it's
because we don't know what Consciousness
is we don't even have a proper
definition of Consciousness so we are
far away from answering this question
Consciousness may possibly have you know
play a role in quantum mechanics
the collapse of the wave function
possibly perhaps I'm not saying it does
we don't know there are lots of
different interpretations of quantum
mechanics out there but yes it's a
possibility it's it's one of the
possibilities that is taken seriously
not by everyone but by certain but
definitely by some physicists you know
it's one of the mainstream
interpretations of consciousness of
quantum mechanics so
unfortunately right now we don't have
any answers to this question very
interesting question but that's what
makes
research in theoretical physics and
quantum mechanics so interesting because
we have these big Mysteries out there
and in Consciousness as well right other
questions other questions
Priyanka says how much do you agree with
everything that velina chakarova from
yesterday's podcast said so I saw these
questions these questions
comments in in the on the podcast and
people some people are very upset people
are very emotional that why did you
bring this person who is very pro-us Pro
Europe I mean what do you guys want I
want to educate you all I want to expose
you all to Different World Views in
different viewpoints understand this it
is very important that you don't listen
to only one Viewpoint in one word you
have to understand how the world is
would you like me to call people who
keep repeating what I always repeat or
would you like to hear the perspective
of other people also you don't have to
agree with it but understand how other
people in different parts of the world
look at events geopolitically and
otherwise
it's important to have an open my open
mind it's important to get exposure and
to get exposed to people from other
parts of the world and see how they
think what is their world view what how
do they look at let's say the Ukraine
war or other things it's important to
listen to people from the U.S from
Europe from China from Pakistan from
Japan from Russia from Africa we have to
listen to different voices only then can
we have broader Horizons you don't have
to agree with everything
the the the guest says and some people
were telling me that it should be a
conversation why why is it the monologue
when I call a guest on the podcast the
focus is on them not on me I speak
enough as it is don't I speak enough
aren't you all familiar with what my
perspective is my biased pro-india
perspective I I'm sure you all everybody
is
so for a change when I get a guest on
the podcast I speak very little I have
that quality I can listen and I never
interrupt my guest and I will never
contradict or disagree with my guest let
them put forth their perspective that is
the whole point of calling a guest and
it's really interesting
to have a conversation or to listen to
with or or to listen to people who have
very different perspectives that
broadens your horizons and then you can
afterwards think about it what she said
or he said or whatever and you can come
to your own conclusions but some people
were saying that I am I am now sold out
because I have given my platform to
somebody who has a different worldview
and different Maybe pro-us pro-west
worldview
come on let's grow up a little bit let's
be a little more mature let's stop
reacting emotionally to everything
my objective when I call guests on the
podcast is to expose you to a wide
variety of World Views and perspectives
that's part of Education these days in
the U.S academic system there is this
concept of a space safe space that we
will not be exposed to to perspectives
and and viewpoints that that offend us
everything is to be safe everybody has
to say the same thing and believe in the
same things that is not the that is not
how you educate anybody that's how you
brainwash people all right so uh
I I think anybody who watches me and
listens to me knows how much I agree
with or don't agree with
what velina said
but it is always instructive
to hear or her viewpoint and that of
other people I'm gonna call other people
from the West in the future and they
will have their own perspective which
will be at odds with my perspective but
I'm going to respect them and I'm going
to give them
the the platform and I want you all to
listen to them so that you understand
you get a better understanding I mean I
I have been speaking about how the West
looks at geopolitics and the Ukraine
conflict and India China relations and
India itself the rise of India but why
not
hear it from somebody who's actually
from there so that's my perspective I I
think we have to be a little more mature
I I know most of my viewers or
significant percentage of my viewers are
young very young people and I'm really
glad that so many young people watch
this I really appreciate that and my
objective is to help you see different
faces of the world all right so I may
not agree with everything my guests say
but I will give them the platform so
that you can learn something
from this interaction
all right
um Sunita says when I share your videos
in WhatsApp my Australian sister-in-law
felt offended about our point of view of
the West how should I react well stop
sharing the videos if she gets offended
when you know lots of people react
emotionally and when the reaction is
negative it's gonna have what's the
point
what's the point how should you react
celavi that's how life is people will
always have different perspectives and
viewpoints and it's all the conditioning
that we go through as children and as
adults we are all conditioned by so many
different sources the education system
the media entertainment industry our
friends our Social Circle it all
conditions us and then when we hear a
Viewpoint that is very different from
that we typically react emotionally and
we get offended how can you say that
things how can you show this share this
sort of video who is this person so what
is the point of doing that don't share
it with her
have a I mean
have a good social life have a good
family life yeah don't don't share such
stuff with that what's the point now
that you know what her perspective is
what is the point
let's let's uh you know have less
friction in life as much as possible uh
pinky Kumari says suddenly the Western
media has started attacking the Dalai
Lama for kissing a kid but does not talk
about Biden kissing young children and
women harassing them my thoughts my
thoughts
it's hypocrisy
first of all uh listen uh Dalai Lama is
a very elderty person the the truth is
that as people get really old they
revert to childlike Behavior okay many
of them I'm not saying all of them some
people they are very sharp you know with
great mental mental acuity deep into the
90s look at Henry Kissinger is still
just as sharp as he was so 50 years ago
really short guy but most people after
their age reach a certain age 60 70
maybe 70 or 80 plus then they kind of
revert back to childlike Behavior the
memories are there the intellect is
there but the behavior becomes more
childlike and they would then tend to do
certain things that they would otherwise
not do right and there is obviously a
cultural disconnect
Tibetan culture has certain customs
every culture has certain Customs that
look very strange when you look at it
from an outsider's perspective okay so
in tibetan culture there is this
tradition of sticking your tongue out in
in greeting in New zealanders in New
Zealand's Maori culture there is this
tradition of greeting people by rubbing
your noses with each other
it's very weird but you've got to
respect that it's it's a cultural
tradition there and it's completely
normal and good over there it doesn't
have any bad meaning or intention
similarly uh so it could be something to
do with culture they greet each other in
Tibet by sticking their tongue out and I
even heard that uh I I don't know the
details but I
will tend to give the Dalai Lama the
benefit of the doubt obviously once this
happened
the pro-china media
has gone all out in their bombarding
social media with all kinds of fake
facts about fake fake stories about how
Tibet was extremely feudal and evil and
they used to sacrifice children and
sacrifice people and enslaved people all
kinds of horror stories that they are
putting out without any shred of
evidence and the evidence I will give
you is that some European went there and
saw it well Europeans have said all
kinds of horrible things about India as
well does it mean those things are true
so please understand and please don't
get swayed by these uh this social media
narrative lots of of people on China's
payroll people who look European or who
are European or American they are also
you know
putting this nonsense out on social
media
so this unfortunately has given the
Chinese Communist Party the CCP a great
golden opportunity to go all out in
demonizing Tibet and justifying their
horrific occupation
of that wonderful Nation okay
so uh I personally give the Delilah the
benefit of the doubt I personally am not
an expert in tibetan culture and customs
I am aware that they greet each other
with the tongue out by sticking the
tongue out and there could be more to it
so I don't think that Dalai Lama is an
evil person
some people do allege that he is a
Chinese agent and all that well I I
don't know about that okay some people
do allege that but I don't know
so uh
so do you see this entire social media
Outburst this outpouring of hate and
vitriol and demonization on the Dalai
Lama on on on on Tibet in tibetan
culture but the same people will be very
quiet when it comes to the the wonderful
propensity and proclivities of President
Biden I mean it's all out there in the
public domain the way he I mean his
behavior his behavior his ghastly
horrific
behavior and nobody speaks about that
that tells you that there that you
cannot trust the media you cannot trust
the media the mainstream media and all
these social media activists who
suddenly have become very
conscious about the alleged atrocities
that were perpeted in Intimate before
the Chinese invaded and conquered and
annexed the nation don't trust this
these are all lies this is a concerted
social media campaign we know in India
about these toolkits you know a whole
bunch of prominent Twitter accounts and
Facebook account and whatnot they start
this concerted campaign all of a sudden
with very similar tweets and very
similar statements all in unison the
trend hashtags and all that this is all
artificially engineered isn't it we
understand that well the same thing is
happening right now with Tibet
and the same people will be completely
quiet when it comes to their president
or the president of the US so this is
hypocrisy it's double standards it's
they are trying to artificially engineer
people's thoughts and sentiments and
they're trying to create a very Pro
China
um
approach environment they're trying to
essentially justify what the Chinese
have been doing you know the horrific
occupation of Tibet which still
continues temporarily so these are my
thoughts about this matter
okay what else
Joy Patel says is the universe infinite
what do you personally think about it I
my personal thoughts are that you know
when I was a kid when I was a kid like
three or four years old I've been
I've been thinking about the universe
and beard stuff nerdy stuff like that
since a very young age okay since I was
very young so I used to wonder you know
the universe
obviously Infinity doesn't make any
sense division by zero doesn't make any
sense I kind of knew it at that age
so I used to think let's say you I I
travel to the end of the universe and
now we are the end so if I try to go
forward what happens do I hit a black do
I hit a you know a hard impenetrable
wall what's beyond that I used to wonder
about it so my my personal thoughts are
that I have no idea
we know that the observable universe is
has a diameter of of roughly 1995
billion light years that's how far we
can see that's the observable universe
that's the Horizon that's the cosmic
Horizon and we know that galaxies are
every day going beyond the observable
Horizon which tells us that there is a
universe out there but it's no longer
accessible to us it's not even visible
to us anymore because of the expansion
of the universe right so I think the
universe is way larger than what we see
that's for sure I personally don't think
it's in finite because Infinity is
non-physical
it doesn't make any sense mathematically
or physically infinity infinity is
essentially you take any number and you
divide by zero that is unphysical that's
a singularity I mean that's the same as
a singularity in black holes which tells
you that your theory doesn't work
so I don't think the universe is would
be in finite I think it will most likely
be way larger than what we see 90 90
billion light years of diameter that's
that's what we see that's a sphere that
we see it's most likely much larger than
that how much larger I have absolutely
no idea of telling you because I don't
know no data when you don't have data
you cannot say
right
um does multiple sexual partners before
pre-manage affect marriage I'm sure it
does I'm sure it does and I don't think
it's a good thing
these days everybody thinks it's a
wonderful thing have they have lots of
Partners I think it's a terrible thing
you know you you don't develop a sense
of loyalty to one person which is very
important in life trust me it's very
important to be loyal to one person in
life life life is not something you take
that lightly but these days because of
media and and all that people think
it's great fun to have lots and lots of
Partners I think it does affect marriage
I don't think it's a good thing right
okay
uh next
Gopi Krishna says how did our ancestors
actually understand understand math how
did they start to interpret math well we
all know if we have one apple and we get
another Apple then we have two apples so
we learn how to count like that I think
even crows and and primates like
chimpanzees gorillas can can count up to
a certain number
and in very primitive human cultures I
don't know I will not take name but they
had like it they could counter to seven
or eight or ten and then the next number
was uncountable yeah
uh
so even non-human uh species some of
them have the ability to count because
you can see right one plus one is two
that you can take a bunch of two and you
take another bunch of two you get four
so um up to a certain number other
species can count some other species not
all of them I mean I'm sure hummingbirds
can't count but chimpanzees and gorillas
and bonobos most likely can count up to
a certain number and so can crows and
I'm sure elephants as well so that
ability is there it's part of part of
the genetic programming of many species
but eventually the Breakthrough that our
ancestors made was the discovery of the
decimal system which gave which suddenly
you know Unleashed
uh Unleashed our mathematical ability
so uh that's how it would have happened
it would have happened very very long
ago the decimal system is most likely a
much more recent uh Discovery and that
the credit for that goes to India
okay
how does astrophysics and space impact
history examples including India
how does astrophysics in space impact
history sometimes there are certain
astrophysical phenomena space phenomena
which kind of imprint themselves
on human consciousness
one I mean
you know there's a very strange thing
out there there is this symbol this
geometrical symbol
that there is one geometrical symbol
that is regarded as sacred
and auspicious
across the planet
for thousands of years and this is
irrespective of where the culture is
whether it's in Africa or in the
Americas or in or in Eurasia or anywhere
else
and that symbol is a swastika now how
did the swastika come about you know
that's a big question most likely it was
a celestial
phenomenon
so we have comets right we know that
comets exist these are Big not big but
you know these dirty dirty snowballs
that come out from the old cloud in in
the outer reaches of the solar system
and as they come closer to the Sun they
get heated by the solar radiation and
the solar wind
and that causes the snow the the water
you know the water to melt and evaporate
and the dust also is released and you
get this big long shining tail because
of the interaction of the solar
radiation so that's how comets develop
Tails as they get heated as they
approach the inner solar system now
sometimes you have a comment with two
tails in very rare occasions you have
comments with three tails and I am sure
that in an extremely rare occasions you
would have a comet with four different
tails
so imagine a situation thousands of
years ago
you have an extremely rare comment
that's very visible
okay across from all around the world
from all around the planet it has four
tails and then this the for some reason
the solar wind causes the comet to
suddenly move like that and then that
cross fourtails becomes swastika
so that's something that if you see ones
you will never forget in your life
you'll remember that and maybe in the
years in in that year was a very good
year perhaps you know extremely good
climate great crops abundance everywhere
and maybe that went on for a decade so
the appearance of that Comet was then
associated with extreme abundance and
prosperity and good luck and all that
and that's something that was then that
continued and still continues so that's
an example
how was Celestial phenomenon can impact
history and the human consciousness and
today the only culture that still
venerates the swastika is Indian culture
and Indian culture spread across Asia
which means the swastika is venerated
wherever you have Hinduism Buddhism and
Jainism
right including
all of Asia Eastern Asia all the way to
Japan so that's an example I could offer
you
okay
um other questions let us see
um
what pratik says what are your views on
veganism is that the way of the future
so veganism is this new fad that exists
in the West for the past few years maybe
decades in which they will eat no animal
products whatsoever not even drink milk
or eat cheese or yogurt nothing nothing
that comes from animal animal products
in India we have never been vegan
historically those in those of us and
our ancestors who did not eat meat would
still consume dairy products
so in India historically traditionally
milk has not been taboo
neither has cheese paneer or or yogurt
curd right
these products have always been consumed
by vegetarians it's never been taboo so
I think veganism is taking it to an
extreme
ridiculous extreme it's about you know
showing that I am morally Superior to
even vegetarians so we in the west are
superior to Indian vegetarians in India
Indian culture which has been doing this
for thousands of years I think veganism
is nonsense I think it's taking things
to our very rather ridiculous extreme
it's not the way of the future and I am
not even opposed to being non-vegetarian
in India people have India obviously
historically has always had the largest
popular percentage or population of
vegetarian people people who did not eat
meat because
um
in our culture we have this
this tradition this precept that means
as far as possible be non-violent don't
inflict unnecessary pain on any living
thing
that doesn't mean that you have to be
passive and accept any nonsense but you
know yeah that so uh don't unnecessarily
harm or cause pain or suffering to any
any living being and that's why it's
always been
seen as morally Superior to not eat meat
but there have always been people
throughout India throughout the ages who
did eat meat right so I think it's a
personal choice I don't think veganism
is a fantastic better way of living life
I don't even think these plant-based
meats and all that are really good I
think it's a I I don't even know what
the purpose is uh clearly certain kinds
of animal agriculture are terrible for
the planet
you know especially the beef industry is
horrible for the planet
um and yeah so one has to
have sustainable
ways of living
so I think vegetarianism is definitely a
superior way I think veganism takes it
to an unnecessary extreme but I am not
against anybody who prefers to eat meat
or whatever it's in you entirely your
personal choice who am I to tell you how
to live your life I think vegetarianism
overall is better for the planet it's
more sustainable and it's better for the
environment and for our future
Generations those who will inhabit the
Earth after we are gone
you know when you do damage to the
planet you are essentially hurting your
descendants
so
that's what I think about this
um
all right
they just says why does the moon not
revolve around itself the moon does
rotate it does it has a period of 28 and
a half days which exactly corresponds to
the time it takes for the moon to do one
revolution around the earth which is why
we only see one phase of the moon
the bright side or the or the there's a
far side also so the Moon is in a
resonance with the Earth it does revolve
but it revolves very slowly that's how
that's how it it happens and you see
this a very similar phenomenon the same
Phenomenon with Pluto and its Moon
Charon they also are in this resonance
Priyanka says if we were to bring back
the ancient Indian system of Education
how would such a school be in this
modern era would it be too drastic to
make Sanskrit the medium of its
Communication in such a school well I
have always been in favor of bringing
back Sanskrit and making it the
civilization civilization language in
India people like me we grew up learning
speaking English learning English it's
almost like our primary uh you know
language of communication
it's terrible it's an example a prime
example a living example of mental
colonization I am myself a great visible
example of mental colonization in this
in the sense that I am more comfortable
with English when it comes to the
subjects I have studied in research to
DP about I I'm not that comfortable
talking about physics for instance in
Hindi
or of the any other language I'm not
talking comfortable talking about
history
in Hindi I I am way more comfortable
expressing myself properly in English
it's unfortunate so I would like the
future generations to not be
mentally colonized in this manner and
the only language that makes sense in
India as the civilization language is
sanskrit I know it's a controversial
statement I know lots of people will
will whatever will say wonderful things
in the live chat about this but yeah the
only language that makes sense is
sanskrit and it's not a dead language so
much of our vocabulary whether it's
north south east west
in the Indian languages comes directly
from Sanskrit if you listen to if you
hear someone speaking in Sanskrit you
can understand most of it it's
definitely a complex language with a
very rich and diverse vocabulary but if
you were taught this from childhood it's
it's the most natural language for any
Indian person to learn it's the easiest
language for an Indian person to learn
uh so I think it's definitely I don't
think it's too drastic to make sense
with the medium of communication you do
it in a phase wise in a phased manner
you know you introduce it first of all
at the nursery level instead of teaching
children a for apple and all the
nonsense you start with Sanskrit all
that
and it can be done up to the college
level in a period of 20 25 years it can
be done slowly casually in a phased
manner
and uh
it's it's a political decision
unfortunately uh the Indian system of
Education was very complicated I mean it
was it was a complex system in The Vedic
Age you had gurukulas but not so in the
let's say the Gupta period or even a
thousand years before today you had this
great Universities at the highest level
and at the lowest level at the
Grassroots level you had temples temples
were the medium of Education where
temples were sent centers of education
so I have like three or four episodes
you know in the ask Abhijit Series in
the in this show
from episode 29 to 33 or something
around that around those episodes in
which I have gone into great detail
about education but what's wrong with
the education system what can be done to
change it uh so in case some of you are
interested in knowing my thoughts in
detail you can look at those episodes
which are fully focused on education I
think it's something we should do
it will be something that will be really
beneficial for everybody in India
especially the future Generations
all right
um
harsh rati says according to you who
would have won
if Julius Caesar and Alexander would
have faced each other in battle
interesting question you ask Julius is
actually as far as I know he
idolized Alexander and he wished that he
could be as great as Alexander was
um Alexander obviously we know that he
rampaged across across Asia he did all
kinds of horrific cruelties which are
kind of kind of whitewashed and not told
we're not told about those things
and eventually he tried to invade India
and well that led to his demise yeah he
he
finally got a very harsh dose of reality
when he came to India tried to invade
India his beloved horse died he himself
got extremely seriously injured and he
limped back to Babylon and over there he
died so that is Alexander but he was a
brilliant strategist tactician great
Soldier one of the great generals of all
greatest generals of all time and so was
Julius Caesar
now Alexander
did not have the resources that Rome had
Julius is a won so many battles he
conquered so many territories he
conquered gold which is the Celtic
territory he conducted a proper genocide
out there which no one speaks about he
even conquered
the English Islands
he uh
conquered Parts he conquered Greece he
conquered Iberia hispania whatever it's
called hispania at the time in parts of
North Africa even Egypt he did a lot I
think if the two have were to face each
other I think if you look at the careers
of both these two uh Guys these two
gentlemen I think Julius Caesar overcame
bigger odds than Alexander and he had
access to better resources than
Alexander so I think if Julius Caesar
and Alexander were to face each other in
battle I think Julius Caesar would come
out on top
and if Julius is there or Alexander had
to face chingy's Khan both of those guys
would have been annihilated by chingis
Khan that's what I believe
right
Kazi aftab says your thoughts on the
recent attack on the Japanese PM yes
today we hear the news that uh during an
election Rally or some political event
in which Japanese prime minister fumio
kishida was participating
a bomb of some kind was was detonated
perhaps in the vicinity or in the
direction of the Prime Minister and uh
if media is to be believed it was a
smoke bomb or something like that so so
a smoke bomb is not a very dangerous
device it's gonna
you know throw off a lot of smoke and
you'll hear a big blast bang that sort
of thing so it's more like a warning
than an actual attempt to kill someone
so what do I think about this well we
know what happened recently Mr female
kishida from his own party you had the
great Shinzo Abe was recently
assassinated recently like in the past
couple of years
um when was it more than a year ago for
sure
Mr Abe was a great possibly the greatest
leader Japan had has had since the end
of the second world war a true Japanese
nationalist somebody who wanted to bring
Japan Japan back as a as a as well an
independent nation right now Japan is
under the U.S occupation he wanted more
power for the Japanese people in the
government well you know what happened
to him now recently we hear that that
Japan has has decided to start
purchasing oil from Russia well that is
obviously a very naughty Behavior if you
look at it from the U.S perspective so
maybe it is uh I'm not I'm not alleging
that this power that power is behind
this thing
uh
so maybe it's a warning to Mr kishida
that don't cross certain lines the next
one won't be a smoke bomb
you know
there is a saying in in Colombia
the saying is
in Spanish means silver
plomo means lead so what is silver
silver is is treasure it's money
silver is precious it's valuable what is
plomo it's lead what is made out of lead
historically they would make bullets out
of lead so when you give somebody the
option of Plata or plomo you're saying
either you take the money the bride that
we're offering you or take the bullet
made out of lead
so maybe this is a way of conveying the
same message to prime minister
it's one you get warned once
you won't be warned again
it's
a possibility
we don't know who who's behind that
typically it's some some lonely person
who does who will be called mentally
deranged or whatever and they'll say
that it was a person Who's acting alone
that's typically the the story you're
given
yeah so I don't know who who was the guy
that killed assassinated prime minister
Abe
uh what happened what what
turned out to be his motifs was he
acting alone and they'll tell you he was
acting alone he was mentally deranged
Disturbed whatever and it's a one-off
incident nothing to do with any politics
or whatever you don't have to believe
all that you know
there have been such other such things
that have happened in the past and
the 1960s for instance
but yeah that's what I think about this
I think it could possibly be a warning
to the prime minister of Japan
says is Zoroastrianism the second oldest
way of life or religion apart from
Hinduism
um Hinduism as we know as far as we know
from the evidence that we have is killed
the oldest way of life or religion uh so
when did so zoroastrinism what we call
Zoroastrianism is something that start
that
emerge from the teachings
of the prophetra
as far as I remember was born in the
city of bulk of or hirath in gandhar not
in Persia itself
and uh
and then he went on to to he had this
Revelation it's the first to really
reveal the religion the first religion
with the prophet and then eventually he
somehow succeeded in getting the Kings
the haksha Manish Kings cabinet Kings of
Iran the Emperors to adopt his religion
and eventually it became Persia's
official state religion or unofficial
State religion but the religion of the
masses
so the question is was there any other
religion that we know of before
the the path of zarathustra
so we don't quite know when zarathustra
was born and when he lived uh assuming
he lived 3000 years ago
um
it could possibly make
them the second oldest religion uh you
know the other Contender is Judaism now
we don't quite know when Judaism emerged
um King Solomon King David Etc they are
supposed to have lived around 800 or 900
BC or thereabouts so and and some people
say that there is some evidence of of
Yahweh the the Jewish god in some
pottery fragment or some kind of such
thing in Egypt but that is obviously
controversial because
it's being interpreted in a certain
manner so that's not hard evidence
so let's assume that Judaism is 2900
years old
lived before that then clearly
Zoroastrianism is the second oldest
known religion
so that's what I can tell you because
the the problem is that we don't know
when
lived what happened is that after the
Arabic invasion of Iran all the
pre-arabic pre-islamic history was wiped
out they in Persia also they would have
had you know textual evidence and
records of the accommended empire in in
the history of Persia until that time
and they would have had lots of fire
temples and all those things none of
that exists today right just like none
of the Great Indian temples in Northern
India still exist or the great
universities all of all of that has been
destroyed but it first happened to Iran
and then it happened to India so
unfortunately in Persia also all the
records of the past of Persia were
destroyed so that's why we don't know
when zoroaster lived and because of that
we don't know what came first whether it
was a rosecranism or Judaism
I would say most likely zarathostra
lived before
the emergence of Judaism so from my
perspective from what I understand from
what I think most likely Zoroastrianism
is the second oldest
religion or way of life after Hinduism
and it emerged out of Hinduism was born
a Hindu obviously in gandhar and then he
created his own path
foreign
let's see something else
India did a reusable rocket test and it
was successful how was it different from
SpaceX what's is what is its future in
the Indian space industry well recently
there was this test of a reusable
vehicle
space vehicle uh I'm not sure if it was
a reusable rocket as such see when you
talk about SpaceX and their reusable
Rockets it's typically the boosters that
they use the first stage booster
booster or boosters that would take a
rocket to a certain altitude
then the boosters are ejected and the
second stage takes off it ignites and it
takes the rocket into orbit that's
typically how it's done and then these
boosters which are ejected typically
historically even with each row these
boosters which are ejected are then
jettisoned into the ocean but with
SpaceX those boosters they go back to a
pre-designated location and they land
themselves upright so that they can be
reused again and again so that saves a
lot of money
now when it comes to ISRO I from what I
know then I kind of know about this uh I
I have not seen any evidence of ISRO
even trying to develop a reusable rocket
or a booster
so the tests that happened recently was
that of a reusable of a of a Glide
vehicle that kind of autonomously landed
itself and it was a scale model which
means not a full-scale model but a small
scale model but it demonstrated that the
technology works so what they did was
that they took this aircraft this
vehicle to a certain altitude
did they they tied it to a heavy lift
helicopter in an Indian Air Force
helicopter
and it was taken to a certain altitude
high up and then it was released
and then this thing the vehicle it
autonomously landed itself you know
without needing any external uh guidance
remote controller or any such thing so
that's what was done so it's kind of a
good step forward
in our technological development So
eventually we will have this kind of
vehicle which can take a heavy cargo
into orbit and then come back
kind of a space shuttle kind of thing in
some sense
and eventually even possibly astronauts
so that's what happened I think it's a
very good step I think there is so much
that the Indian space industry can do so
what's that ISRO can do and nowadays we
have seen the uh in recent times we've
seen the entry of private companies in
their space launch industry I think it's
a very good sign
um
so I think overall there's a huge amount
of potential untapped potential in the
Indian space industry there are so many
brilliant Engineers who want to get into
this you know who want to do this I I
really wish the government would would
unleash this potential give people the
opportunity people with great ideas give
them the funding and give them some time
to see to to make their ideas work
obviously not all ideas will work there
will be many failures but that is the
process you have to go through
that's the process you to go through so
I think there's a huge amount of
potential in India the future clearly is
very bright but I would hope to see some
acceleration of the process I would like
to see some ambition and some Hunger
within ISRO I'm sure there are lots of
ambitious and hungry engineers in ISRO
who would be telling them why can't we
go ahead and surpass SpaceX just give us
the funds give us the go ahead and we'll
do it
I think that that's something that needs
to happen it doesn't take a huge amount
of money to do that I would like to see
Israel's budget doubled instead of
instead of curtailed that's what's
happening right now so I don't know
anyway the government knows what's best
I assume I I suppose
but it's uh yeah
kind of disappointing
all right
has been saying interesting things of
late he went to China he met with
President Xi Jinping and he tried to
bring China
to towards his Viewpoint of for for
making Russia see reason and convincing
Russia to abandon its terrible Ukraine
war or whatever that obviously did not
work Mr Xi Jinping showed a great deal
of impatience when he was being told all
this
um
and macaw is trying to
like like I've always said the only
nation within NATO that has a somewhat
independent somewhat quasi-independent
foreign policy that nation is France
that's the only nation that has its own
nuclear Warheads that are within its own
control it has its own nuclear
submarines that nobody else controls
and it is obviously constrained by being
a part of NATO but it has some
Independence compared to Nations like
the UK or Germany or Italy or whatever
else
so
France has historically been a nation
that has chafed at these chains
you know they have always they they have
a thousand year enmity
with the British with the English not
the British but the English
so the French and the English have
historically been
antagonists enemies there have been you
know small periods of time when they
have kind of collaborated or cooperated
but typically mostly it's been a
thousand years of enmity
and now that the capital of the
Anglo-Saxon Empire has moved from London
to Washington that's that's the enmity
but
after 1945
Western Europe Western Europe has been
ruled by the Americans and controlled by
the Americans so the French have always
shaved at being being placed under such
constraints uh the French leader Charles
the goal
tried he himself spoke about this that
we need to distance ourselves from NATO
and he did take France out of the core
group of NATO it was still part of NATO
but you know
a certain amount of autonomy for for
some years it's only the 21st century
that France rejoined the the core
workings of NATO
uh
so Mr Macon obviously is a continuation
of that Legacy of the tradition of
France wishing it was independent again
and these comments have to be seen in
that light and obviously it is an
indication of the fact that America's
influence is kind of on the decline it's
decreasing and when this happens lots of
Nations will try
and explore opportunities
of of loosening the grip
that the US has had on them for decades
so this was all comment I mean it's it's
it's
remarkable that in the last year or two
this word which was kind of obscure
and not a mainstream would has now
become so mainstream the V word vasal
maybe I have something to do with it
small some small amount perhaps
okay
uh what do we have what do we have I've
spoken about mithanis lots of times
um
Amit degada says what is your view on
the recent U.S confidential documents
leak it appears like this was a planted
leak not a real leak
uh that's the that's the sense I get I
have not really looked into the
documents and done a deep dive and
researched all this uh there's so much
happening right now it could very well
be part of a bigger misinformation
campaign to make it look like certain
things exist but you know something else
is brewing somewhere else uh I I get the
feeling the sense I that this may be a
planned leak which means that it doesn't
really
tell you the truth that's the sense that
I get maybe I will do a deeper dive into
it and maybe come to a different
conclusion perhaps but I think that's
that's the feeling that I get
okay
why do you think communal hate is
increasing in India I see kids these
days joking about these things and
teasing each other what can be done to
correct this you know
we are being told that India is becoming
more communal and there's more hatred I
don't think so
social media they say that this it's all
because of social media that everybody
is now being
radicalized and and the divisions in the
nation are becoming Starker it's not the
case what I think and what I see is that
social media has simply brought out the
device that already existed
okay they have social media simply
brought out in the Limelight the
divisions that already existed
these divisions have been created by
Outsiders and then they have been
perpetuated by certain political outfits
certain political outfits I am not
naming anyone's name
but they have been perpetuated by
various politicians and political
outfits not all I'm sure some for their
own political benefit
so over time after 1947 we have seen a
deepening of these divisions
so that's been done by politicians
social media hasn't exacerbated this it
simply brought it out into the public
eye that's what happened
um
what can be done to correct this we need
this really
I think what India needs is a way
stronger central government
more centralization
and obviously a good government you know
not not
the right government the right
leadership
there's too much federalism in India too
much is is
this you know
states are given too much power in some
in some ways
in some ways there is so much a state
can do and the central can't intervene
because it's you know some some things
are
um the Dominion of the state
and this is especially dangerous in
certain some perhaps border states I
would imagine perhaps
so I think the entire system that has
been created after 1947 is is
responsible for the situation that we
have right now what we need is a totally
revamped and different system a new
constitution maybe a presidential system
perhaps or as a different system maybe
something similar to what we had
before in before the past 1000 years of
humiliation that India has suffered
something that reverts back to our that
goes back to our
cultural and civil civilizational Roots
that's what India actually needs
um
yeah
right
what else do we have
custom says is everything part of
solipsism is everything really true or
maybe a dream look I am not a
philosopher I don't know possible it's a
possibility it's a possibility that
everything we see and touch and imagine
and feel may all be made up by our own
mind and we may be all alone in the
universe and we are just dreaming all of
this there's no real way of knowing it
right
because everything we see everything we
observe comes through certain senses
sense organs the eyes the years
and all that data goes into the brain
and in into the mind and it's only then
that we can make sense of it so what if
the only
person that exists in the world is is
you
and I'm Just an Illusion I'm just
something that your sensory organs made
up that's also a possible possibility
you know so that's the solipsistic
School of thinking school of thought or
School of philosophy so I don't know
right I don't know I don't know the
answers I I do interact with all kinds
of people they seem to be very real to
me
you know but who knows who knows who
knows maybe everything is just a dream
so that's philosophy and I'm not a
philosopher so I can't really go deep
into it but it's an interesting thought
to have
trippy solipsism
okay ramayan Raj Singh says during the E
during the early years of the Indian
nation state it was necessary to be
socialist in order to better control the
population and by extension keep the
state United my thoughts my thoughts
imagine a different scenario okay we had
socialism
was Mr nehru able to keep the the the
the nation the state United he gave
chunks of territory he gave away the
cocoa Islands to Burma he gave away the
Cabo value of Manipur to Burma again he
gave away parts of of accepting to the
Chinese after they gave away Tibet to
China he gave away parts of arunachal to
the Chinese
property
so what does that have to do with
socialism you know and so of course he
was socialist so if if this is socialism
then it was better not to have socialism
now imagine let's do a thought
experiment imagine instead of Mr nehru
imagine supposed
now people say he was a fascist people
alleged that he was a fascist he did say
that he wanted 20 years of dictatorship
imagine that subashita Bose came to
power and he imposed 20 years of iron
rule dictatorship do you think the
population would not have been in
control then imagine a verse imagine a
more drastic scenario I'm nothing worse
probably wrong word imagine a more
drastic scenario Instead This is a
thought experiment imagine
hypothetically instead of nehru and
Gandhi you had Joseph Stalin ruling
India a person like Joseph Stalin
iron rule no descent tolerated do you
think the population would not have been
uncontrolled
and do you think he would have allowed
he would have do you think a person like
Stalin would have
supplied the rice to the invading
Chinese soldiers in Tibet no he would
have actually sent the Indian army to
boot the Chinese out of Tibet and then
perhaps he may have a next Tibet himself
and you think he would have allowed the
pakistanis to take over be okay he would
have ended Pakistan right there India
had the resources to destroy a nation
like Pakistan
and they had the all the resources of
the British Union Army and the Navy and
the Air Force the Indian Navy of the
time
was one of the most powerful names in
the world
it was used by the British to control an
enormous territory from the Gulf of
Malacca depends from the state of
Malacca to the Strait of Hormuz in the
Persian Gulf enormous territory which
was all controlled by the British
through the Indian Navy
so let's not kid ourselves
it was not necessary to be the Socialist
to control the population
socialism was used to
destroy the Indian economy three percent
four percent growth they they
pejoratively call it the Hindu rate of
growth it was the nehruvian rate of
growth
India
in 1947
India's GDP was less than two percent of
the global GDP and India's
uh life expectancy was around 30 maybe
32 maybe 28 give or take a couple of
years that was a disaster a nation like
that could only go up and here it was
prevented from going up so I think
socialism was a great evil I think Mr
Nero deliberately delayed India's Rise
by many decades and and his successes
also did that I think socialism was a
great curse for the people of India
what did it do to control the population
what you need to control a population is
a strong state
and India's population is not a
rebellious population India's population
go out in the streets of any large city
in India to did you see cops anywhere go
to New York you'll see cops everywhere
take away the cops from New York City
for 15 minutes and you'll see riots in
looting and arson
that's what you call a police presence
total
constant 24x7 patrolling in New York
City
and contrast that with any large Indian
city you'll hardly see cops anywhere and
if the cops are there they would be
sitting there just to show their
presence because they've been told to do
so India the people of India are not
rebellious violent people
okay mainly
mainly so I don't think
that it was necessary to be socialized
to control the population the population
doesn't need control
the population is a very civilized law
abiding population so yeah that is my
answer to this question but interesting
question that you've asked sir
okay
was shingles Khan cruel he allegedly
killed 10 of the population some people
have written that he killed these many
people of that many people where's the
evidence where is the evidence see we
read textbooks but understand that most
textbooks are someone's opinion they are
not based on facts
show me the evidence that 10 percent of
whatever population was killed show me
archaeological hard evidence
you go to Paris
there is something called The Catacombs
of Paris okay under the City of Paris
there are these huge this is huge
network of tunnels all right
it's full of dead bodies skeletons
you know how many people are there
several there are the remains of several
million people
how did so many people die
no one will tell you
nobody will tell you how so many people
died and it's not from hundreds of years
ago it's more like the past three four
hundred years
so what event happened in the past three
400 years that several million people
died and they were all buried in these
Catacombs of Paris nobody has an answer
that is archaeological evidence of
millions of people dying
Now where's the evidence that changes
can't kill so many people
the only accounts we have of Genghis
Khan's campaigns and his career
is one the secret history of the Mongols
and secondly
the accounts of his enemies
yeah
and there is no archaeological evidence
anywhere of the of him killing X number
of people or Y number of people
so whatever we read in this book's
history books and all these are opinions
of writers typically European or Western
writers
and they can't digest the fact that a
guy from the East was greater than their
Alexander and their Julius Caesar and
their Napoleon
and so the demon as him
the accusing of all kinds of things even
worse things than killing ten percent of
a Region's population
so I completely disagree with this
allegation that chingis Khan killed ten
percent or whatever number of people
some say I don't know 50 million 100 I
don't know what the number they throw
around
there is absolutely no hard evidence for
that zero zero heart evidence the other
story is that he he is the he is the
ancestor of iron or ten percent of the
world's population today once again zero
evidence absolutely zero evidence but
it's accepted as a fact today people
will come and tell you this that he
raped so many women and so many people
are his descendants show me the evidence
show me evidence and what is the
evidence how do we find evidence of that
first of all you will need Genghis
Khan's own DNA only then can you prove
or claim such a thing we don't have
evidence of it we don't have his DNA
anywhere
his body has never been found
we don't even have the DNA of his
descendants we may have DNA samples of
his
of descendants who came far after him
many many generations Generations after
impossibly
that's not evidence
was it cruel he was a hard man he went
you have no idea what this guy went
through
to succeed he had a horrific childhood
he saw things nobody should see he had
to undergo things nobody should undergo
and he was able to come out on top and
succeed he was able to unify his nation
in his mid-40s only until his mid-40s
from childhood until his mid-40s he was
battling all kinds of
odds
and then he unified his nation and he
launched his career as a conqueror in
his mid or late 40s and in 20 years he
conquered more territory than Roman
emperors were able to conquer in 300
years so yes obviously he was a military
expansionist but he only he only
conquered in retaliation he only went to
war when there was a just cause for war
and some people don't agree with me well
you can take a hike I don't care those
of you who don't agree go somewhere else
see see the account of somebody who who
agrees who who agrees with what you
think
so um
was it cruel I don't think it was
unnecessarily cruel but obviously he
bought so many battles he waged the
entire military campaigns people would
die in that that's something that every
single conqueror did including Julius
Caesar including Napoleon including
Alexander
including samudra Gupta including Ashoka
including
kanishka the great
and so on so forth right so I don't
think he was specifically or especially
cruel but yeah that's the kind of image
they have created of this man I think
he's
he was better in my opinion than most of
these so-called conquerors who are
glorified
uh no I said take a hike I did not say
anything else
all right all right
okay
vinay Singh man says who um sorry what
is the origin of the haryanvi language
why is it called a dialect of Hindi and
why not Punjabi Nepali Gujarati Marathi
why are these languages not called
dialects of Hindi which one is older see
they have artificially placed the Hindi
at the top and made it the national
language and then every other language
that sounds kind of similar to it will
be called a dialect of Hindi these
goddamn linguists don't know what they
are doing Linguistics Indian Linguistics
needs to be looked at a priori from
scratch from zero that's what needs to
happen what's the origin of the haryana
haryanvi language clearly an older
prakrit language there were so many
prakrits
in India
these brackets all emerged out of
Sanskrit
even Pali can be considered to be a
paragraph it was it was an upper Branch
form of Sanskrit the broken down kind of
corrupted
form of Sanskrit so you had so many
practice several generations of prakrit
one of the brackets one of the brackets
I can think of is Maharashtra which was
spoken about 13 1400 years ago it
eventually gave birth to a number of
languages including president Dave
Marathi
you had an old gurjari language which
gave birth to a number of languages
including Gujarati including mewadi
marwadi Etc and there would have been
other prakras that gave rise to
languages like Punjabi haryanvi Etc
yeah so we don't quite know because our
historians once again have not done this
work they have not delved deep into the
linguistic history of India
the Romani people speak various Romani
dialects which are I would say most
closely related to Sindhi Rajasthani and
Gujarati
that's an interesting linguistic path
that the Romani languages have taken
so there is so much research that can be
done in India
Indian Linguistics is a gold mine for
linguists but they will not touch it
because they have certain agendas
so my my point is that we don't quite
know what's the origin of the haryanvi
language why don't we I would like to go
and visit the University of Chandigarh
and and speak to some history professors
there you know imminent historians and
ask them this question do they have an
answer they will not have any answer
because they have not been doing
anything
they will only open a textbook and read
out of it and they'll tell you go and
study this and that's the some of these
things will be in the exam at the end of
the year that's unfortunately however
academicians have been
extremely low standards in India
that's why I keep telling you all please
raise your standards don't accept
mediocrity
95 of our academic
uh
you know members of the academic system
are
mediocre to be kind to them to be kind
so uh
so
so why is Punjabi not a dialect of Hindi
you know
all of these languages they took various
different paths you know and they had
different ancestral practice languages
and most of in all these brackets came
out of Sanskrit so Punjabi sounds very
different from Hindi doesn't it Nepali
sounds kind of different from Hindi
Gujarati in Marathi they sound different
from each other and from Hindi as well
Gujarati and
marwadi sound very similar Gujarati and
Sindhi sound quite similar
Marathi is kind of
the
kind of it sounds more like similes
actually sinhala
seem to be connected in some strange way
so it's it's a fascinating thing you
know Indian Linguistics but we don't
have the answers because
and the thing is I personally
perhaps may be capable if I apply myself
of doing this research but I can't fight
every battle unfortunately I can't I can
only pick and choose certain battles I
have one lifetime
and I can only do that much so much in
that so that's why I don't know
I can only tell you what what knowledge
is available to us and the origin of the
haryanvi language unfortunately we don't
know which older language it came out of
so there we are that's where we are
today
but yes if you are in in Chandigarh or
somewhere around there please go to the
university of Chandigarh or any other
university
and find one of the eminent historians
there and ask this question
please ask this question and let's see
what if they have any answer I can
guarantee they have no answers
Joseph Stalin says will Russia become a
junior partner of India since India is
officially the biggest purveyor of
Eurasian oil as far as you know China
even today it Imports more oil from
Russia than India does but
so let's the so imagine hypothetically
that by next year India is importing
more oil from Russia than even China
okay imagine that does it mean that
Russia will become a junior partner of
India I think Russia has options
Russia has many options it has India it
has China it has other nations Iran
it has Iran
so you become someone's Junior partner
if you have no option but to go to them
and there's nobody else for you
and when they are in a more advantageous
position as compared to you means they
have the money and you have something
you want to sell them and you have no
option but to sell only to them and then
they can call the shots they can dictate
the terms of the engagement that's when
you become a junior partner I don't see
Russia becoming a junior partner of
India or of China even
um the recent uh foreign policy
or the revised foreign policy that they
have put out recently explicitly states
that uh that from Russia's perspective
China and India are going to be the top
two International partners for Russia so
they clearly have accorded the special
relationship to China and India
and
in the future hypothetically
hypothetically you know if India and
China could somehow
let's say finalize the boundary
then
things would really change in
geopolitics because then the Ric
grouping could emerge that would be a
big challenge to any hegemony in the
world if these two Nations these three
nations can could possibly
hypothetically in the future work
together so I don't see Russia because
becoming a junior partner of India
and Russia in India could benefit
greatly from each other actually more
than Russia and China could benefit from
each other
because China will never give Russia
access to the warm warm season the warm
Waters of the so-called South China Sea
Etc are
are right now under a great deal of
contention the Chinese are claiming this
region but there is a lot of
um it's it's not a faith accompli for
them
and uh
and the Russians have a significant
amount of
influence then a degree of control in
central League we haven't opened the map
how can it be
let's open the map let's talk about
about this with with the map
where is the map where is the map here
is the map okay so look at the geography
Russia in India why do I say they can
benefit greatly from each other
India has access
to the warm Waters of the Indian Ocean
enormous Coastline that's what India has
and Russia has enormous an enormous
amount of territory which contains maybe
half of the world's natural resources
oil and gas and coal and iron and other
raw materials
and obviously agricultural land so
Russia has all of that but what Russia
lacks is access to a warm water Port
Vladivostok is not a warm water plot so
if Russia which has a lot of influence
in Central Asia
Etc if Russia could somehow
success India's warm water ports it will
be a game changer for Russia as well as
for India
and India and Russia don't have any bone
of contention
or any dispute of any kind with each
other so all that stands in the way
is Pakistan occupied Kashmir let's see
how long that lasts
all right
okay
okay let's see other questions
who has committed more atrocities USA or
USSR
come on it's the Anglo-Saxon Empire
but they are the masters of propaganda
you won't even believe
if someone says that they have committed
more atrocities That's The Power of
propaganda
in the 20th century the Americans used
to say that the Russians are masters of
propaganda and these people like Yuri
benjaminov and Etc they came out and
they exposed certain Russian techniques
and means of doing propaganda well
believe me the Americans are orders of
magnitude ahead of the Russians when it
comes to propaganda
so there you go
okay
avishik Abhishek Abhishek let's let's
call it Abhishek what did our early
Vedic ancestors what term did they use
to call the religion I think the the
term for what we now call religion
was Dharma which means the right path
it was not called Hinduism the term
Hindu did not even exist at the time
Hinduism is an exonym name given by
Outsiders to Indian India's
religion so to say it's not just one
religion it's a whole bouquet of
religions which is essentially all the
same thing in different ways so I think
what our early Vedic ancestors would
call it the most the closest term would
be Dharma
but I think Dharma is the
better word for what our religion was in
those days Dharma
okay what else
some other questions Let's uh
okay Watson 12 years ago
edited says was there any influence of
the Indus Valley Civilization on the
Mahabharata first of all we have to
understand that the Indus Valley
Civilization was actually the Saraswati
Sindhu phase of Indian civilization it
was not some separate civilization that
has disappeared and we have no idea what
it is we are a continuation of that the
people who lived in that era and in that
geography were our ancestors all of us
will have some ancestry that comes from
that region especially no matter where
you are in the country you will have
some ancestry that comes from there and
so it was one phase of India's
civilizational history it was not some
separate civilization like your teachers
you know textbooks teach you
so it was a Saraswati Hindu phase of
India's history and civilization was
there any influence of that on the
Mahabharata well that depends on when
the Mahabharata happened and there is
still
we still don't have
uh clear understanding of what is what
of when the Mahabharata happened so a
variety of different researchers who I
all respect I have the greatest respect
for all of them these people have all
come up with different different dates
based on how they have calculated uh
done the calculations based on mainly RQ
astronomy
and unfortunately they all fight amongst
each other it's very very visible public
fight on social media all the time it's
uh unfortunate so I personally am
neutral I have no favorite date so my
point is I don't know when the
Mahabharat happened
okay
various researchers have made various
claims all of them have certain
positives certain drawbacks
so until this entire matter is settled I
will not say that so and so was the date
of the Mahabharata
the point is we don't know when it
happened assuming it happened before
5000 BC assuming
it happened even before 3000 BC
then possibly this phase of Indian
history would could have influenced the
Mahabharata and if you read the text of
the Mahabharata it's clearly not a
pastoral India that you see Pastor
Robin's rural agriculture in India
mentions lots of different cities
lots of different kingdoms it mentions
the entire geography of Jammu with the
entire subcontinent from Gandhara to the
Himalayas all the way to the southern
part of India
east to west
so it looks like the Mahabharata the
events of the Mahabharat War happened
during a time when India was no longer a
rural Agricultural Society
we had lots of Kingdoms lots of cities
it sounds kind of like the Saraswati
Hindu phase of India's history
you know it sounds like that if you look
at if you if you study the text
so it's possible that maybe these these
events and the thing is that if you look
at all these archaeological sites
these are modern names for these places
we don't know what the people of that
time called call the cities harappa is
what we now call this archaeological
site it doesn't mean that 5000 years ago
the inhabitants of the city called it
harappa I am sure they did not call it
that they would have called it with some
other name which we have lost
same for
mohenjo daro it's a sense it's a it's a
Sindhi word for a mound of the Dead
the people of that who lived in the city
in its peak or even in its in its
infancy would not have called it mohenjo
daro
so we don't know the names we don't know
the name of us this the original name of
a single archaeological site of the
Sarasota and there are thousands of
archaeological sites that we know of
so possibly one could look at the text
of the Mahabharata and try to understand
the geography and what what the names
could be possibly
so I think there could be a connection
between the Saraswati Sindhu phase of
India's history and the Mahabharata
because the geography of the Bharat is
very different from the from the earlier
geography of the ramayan which itself
has mentions of lots of Kingdoms and
place names
it's only when you come to the rigveda
that we that we see a very different
India a fully Agricultural and pastoral
India so I think the Mahabharata was at
a much later more advanced stage of
India's history and it's possible that
the time period of the Mahabharata could
possibly coincide with the time period
but one of the time periods of the
Saraswati Hindu phase of our history but
unfortunately we don't know which phase
because we don't know the exact date of
the mahabara or even the century in
which the Mahabharata happened thus far
people have made calculations and I have
the utmost respect for the amount of
work they've done in arriving at their
conclusions but we don't have a proper
consensus yet as to which of these
claims is correct because these claims
are very very widely differing claims so
we can't say
okay
you said pedifiers thank you for opening
my eyes to how geopolitics works it's
not about emotions sentiments or down
through individuals geopolitics is hard
called truths and pursuing national
interests correct and you're most
welcome it is that's what geopolitics is
it's all about power it's a pursuit of
power and control and territory and
resources that's what it is
okay
all right let's see some other other
questions
um
so sanjit says are UFO sightings real
I suppose some of them may be real
and we have lots of aerial phenomena
Celestial phenomena that look very
strange sometimes
I remember back in the day when I was a
student doing my master's degree
that time once in the evening I had
ventured out of where I was staying
evening walk with some friends
in the sky we witnessed an astonishing
site an entire galaxy so to say
of little meteors which are burning up
in the atmosphere
and I kind of realized at the time that
it's probably the re-entry of some
defunct satellite or maybe a space
station or something in between
it was it was not that rapid meteor that
you know disappears in a second it was
burning up slowly and traveling very
slowly up in the atmosphere
so yeah I mean I understood what it was
but somebody else might have mistaken it
for some alien phenomenon UFO phenomenon
so what I'm trying to say is that many
if not most of these strange
phenomena or sightings
have
a physically explainable origin and
mostly you can explain it off explain it
without having to bring in Aliens into
the picture okay but I'm sure there are
certain some sightings Somewhere over
the other which may not be so easy to
explain
uh so I'm open to the possibility that
some of these things may involve
possible alien activity I'll be I'll be
very happy if aliens were to visit Earth
it would be possibly the greatest moment
in thousands of years of human history
possibly
but yeah we don't know
so are these sightings real possibly but
we don't have hard evidence all the
photographs that we see all the video
that we see is typically grainy and
blurred
typically grainy and blurred and black
and white the U.S military releases
these this video of alleged UFOs or
whatever they call uaps they have
extremely sensitive equipment camera
equipment that can take very sharp you
know pictures and videos of whatever
happens and they still released grainy
black and white images why
if they really want to prove to the
world that this actually happens and
exists why don't they release the full
definition Videos HD videos or 4K videos
they want
so that's why it sounds fishy I have not
seen
even one such video
or photograph that truly astonishes me
and and stumps me
and I'm not able to explain what it is
you know it's always blurry it's always
grainy it's often black and white
and it's often something that you can
that you can you know spoof using photo
manipulation image manipulation software
so so the answer is in the absence of
evidence all I can say is I don't really
know maybe some of it is real but I have
not seen any evidence of that
okay
um
what else what else what else
go extinct in the world well if you look
at the UK it's a monarchy
they have a king
Charles is the king the second Charles
of all time his mommy was the queen so
you have a monarchy in the UK
look at Saudi Arabia they have a king
and they have a Crown Prince Mohammed
bin Salman
look at the island of Tonga they have a
king do you know where Tonga is
uh let's go to the map
Tonga is in the South Pacific you know
where India is let's go eastwards and
southwards we cross the equator goes out
of the Equator go east of Australia
Australia you have New Caledonia you
have Fiji and south east of Fiji you
have Tonga the capital of Tonga is Nuku
alofar shall we find where it is
where is Nuku other it is
the capital of Tonga
see I'm a total nerd I know all these
weird names
so this little nation state
in the South Pacific has a king
I don't remember who the king is but
yeah
so you have Tonga which is a monarchy
you have the UK which is a monarchy I
saw the Arabia which is a monarchy Japan
is a constitutional monarchy where the
king
uh akihito
whoever it is this is is the titular
Head of State uh you have various
monarchies in Europe which still exist
and of course you have an Empire
the Anglo-Saxon Empire which is ruled by
God knows who somebody does rule it they
have presidents and all but that's only
a name we know that
so you have Empires you also have the
Chinese Empire the Chinese Communist
party which is a new Dynasty
China always goes through dynastic
Cycles dynasties rise and fall with a
period of complete chaos in between
so the CCP is a dynastic cycle and the
current Emperor is region ping so you
know you can give it whatever name you
want you can call it a democracy you can
call it the Constitutional this or that
but you have monarchists today and you
do have Empires as well India obviously
is a nation state that is what it is
today so India is no longer a monarchy
we have abolished the Monarch the the
the the the kingdoms that we used to
have in my opinion many of these Kings
and kingdoms and queens they actually
did much better for India than
the post 1947 certain regimes did but
they are that's just how it is so so
that's how it is so it's not really
extinct it seems to be extinct it's made
to look like it's extinct but it's not
really extinct
Star-Lord Star Lord says where homes
Hindu before they came to India the
homes uh see today the people of Assam
are not pure homes they call they're
called homes but the
a certain
they have a certain amount of ancestry
they see the people of Assam today have
very mixed so to say ancestry
they will have some ancestry which is
which is a significant Affinity with the
people of Bengal some ancestry which
with affinity to the people of odisha
some Affinity which is some ancestry
which is which has more Affinity with
the other states of Far East India like
Manipur nagaland tripura Etc some
ancestry which is closer to
that sort of thing and some ancestry
which is Thai Thai ancestry map again
where's the map
so the Thai people are in the ethnic
group it's no linguistic group
that have given their name to Thailand
or Thailand
some of them also live in northern Laos
and the Yunnan province which is
currently temporarily part of China has
historically been a Thai region the
people who live there are not Han
Chinese they are the majority are Thai
now some of these people
in the past sometime in the past
thousand or so years some of them
migrated into in what is now uh Assam in
India
and they obviously assimilated into the
population that already lived there and
their descendants are the group that are
now called the Assamese people and
historically they were called the home
people the home Kingdom and all that so
the question is these people the Thai
people who came to India at the time
where the Hindu when they came to India
they were most likely not Hindu they
clearly were a polytheistic people they
were neither Buddhists nor Hindu you
know if you if you want to make a
distinction they were definitely a
polytheistic people just like how the
Northeast the Far East of India used to
be before the christianization of the
region
so if you look at the various peoples
of what we call Northeast India actually
the it should be called the Far East of
India before the crystallization of this
region which was artificially done by
the British and then by Mr nehruji uh
the peoples of this region all had
polytheistic belief systems
uh there was animism which is Spirit
Worship there was nature worship there
was uh ancestor worship
and other gods and goddess so the there
were these entire pantheons of gods and
goddesses in such life so the Thai
people also had the same thing and they
came into India and eventually it became
the OM people so that's how history
uh happened that's how this entire
process happened
says why are there so many civil wars in
the Middle East and Africa well you have
to ask yourself who is which
who is the major power in the Middle
East and who is the major power in
Africa
once again let's go to the map
so when it comes to the Middle East you
have
you can call it the Middle East or you
can call it uh West Asia whatever you
want to call it
the major power in this region is the
United States of America
okay they have typically the you can see
all these straight line borders over
here which were drawn by the British and
the Americans
in the first half of the 20th century
and in the past 70 80 years
it is the Americans who have been the
major power here and if this region is
in turmoil you have to uh ask yourselves
how that happened the Middle East is
always in crisis why is it so who
creates this crisis
and now that the American influence is
declining in this region
why is the Middle East stabilizing why
are Iran and Saudi Arabia shaking hands
now
in case some of you watched my podcast
with willina chakarovashi herself said
this that U.S influence in West Asia or
the Middle East whatever you call it is
declining and the region is now
stabilizing I think
one leads to the other one has clearly
led to the other the stabilization has
happened because he was influence in
this region is declining and their
interest is declining because they're
known no longer need Saudi oil
similarly ask yourself who is the major
power in Africa
so when it comes to Western Africa
much of it is
you could say still de facto colonized
by France
and when it comes to the remaining
nations in Africa many of them are very
strongly under
U.S influence
right and these nations have propped up
lots of dictatorships in Africa
for the past 70 80 years at least ever
since colonization officially ended more
or less but they have kept these Africa
in in turmoil in strife
and they have also done lots of regime
change operations when somebody comes up
see you know what happens in Africa
what happens in Africa
Africa is being used to produce
consumer
uh
crops
for the West
so all these nations in Africa they have
so much fertile soil
they have such wonderful resources
yeah but none of these African nations
grows rice or wheat
they grow exotic crops like coffee
coffee
and other things which are all exported
to the West so the West gets what it
wants and in return it IT Supplies rice
in wheat Etc to the African nations and
God forbid some African ruler decides
president decides that we should now
stop you know growing cocoa and all
these crops and start growing rice and
wheat for ourselves something happens
and this guy gets knocked off
so because African nations don't are not
allowed to grow their own crops they are
always forever dependent on the west
for feeding their people
and if they Implement certain policies
that the West does not like the West can
starve them on demand
foreign
Africa which all use
the French franc or various African
versions of the French franc which are
printed in France and the French take
you know they charge money for printing
the currency
so Africa is still colonized and that's
why it is because of the malign
influence of the West that there are so
many civil wars in middle in the Middle
East in Africa
and why Africa is so deeply impoverished
despite being so incredibly resource
Rich there are nations in Africa that
are they produce enormous amounts of
gold but these nations have zero gold
reserves so where does all the gold go
ask yourselves
colonization has never ended
and the West is still destroying these
nations understand these things
your history teacher will not teach you
any of this most likely your registered
teacher doesn't even know about this and
if they know they will not teach you why
ask yourself why
because they want to fool you they want
you to live in a make-believe world and
not understand how the real world works
anyway
teaching says do I diet I try to I don't
really really diet I try to eat healthy
but it doesn't always work especially
when I'm traveling I
I try to eat one meal a day but as you
can see I'm reasonably healthy right now
so yeah it doesn't always work off late
I have been a little bit uh
indisciplined so to say
uh so I need to get my diet so to say
back back on track I mean one meal a day
and go to gym more regularly build up
some more muscles yeah but um I don't
diet as such I mean I don't really cut
certain things out of my out of my diet
I like to eat if you eat just one meal a
day you're gonna typically eat healthy
right
so that's what I try to do
okay we have crossed the two uh two hour
mark
so
what's my guilty pleasure my guilty
pleasure I enjoy lots of things I enjoy
lifting weights I really enjoy that
that's a it's not a guilty pleasure it's
a pleasure I embrace
what else do I enjoy I enjoy reading I
enjoy music good music
I don't have any guilty pleasure as such
yeah I sometimes like to eat sweet food
or even eat Savory food I have lots of
Pleasures I don't think any of these is
especially guilty yeah so I don't have
any bad habits as such I mean I don't
indulge in alcohol or any such thing so
so my guilty pleasures are typically
reasonably good guilty pleasures
okay
yes Martin says do not eat sugar I agree
sugar is not good
sugar essentially if you take it in
sufficient quantities it starts acting
like a poison
so it's not something the body needs
it's it's nice it tastes good that's why
we all like it but yeah I agree do not
eat sugar as far as possible and sugar
takes different forms you eat bread
bread it gets converted into glucose in
the body it's the same thing as eating
sugar you know so people I have known
people who diet
so they will drink tea but not put those
two teaspoons of sugar in there but they
will eat bread they will eat pasta they
will eat all kinds of other garbage so
that so I used to ask myself what's
what's the point of of not putting those
two teaspoons of sugar in your in your
tea
so yeah I agree do not eat sugar sugar
is is not something that we need it's
not necessary of course if you are
healthy and fit you can eat sugar
but yeah
but overall don't
um
Dr Jai Shankar supervisor says if Dowry
system isn't Indian or a Hindu custom
who brought the system in our nation is
it the British who inherited this just
like the integrated their caste system
into the Indian Society look in India we
had jati and Verna it's been there for a
very very very very long time but this
system of four divisions the system was
created by the British we had jati Verna
we have always had this
but this system that we have today that
when we any when somebody is born we
have to fill in the birth certificate
write a certain cast one of these four
divisions that has been created
institutionalized by the British okay so
you have to identify forcibly as one of
these four divisions the jati Verna
system is way more complicated than that
and way more nuanced than that the
British could not wrap their little
heads around that so they oversimplify
it and created this four division system
Now read what megastani said right the
Greek ambassador to the modern Court he
said there were seven classes in India
so it's not
so this is this is a foreign system
that's been force-fitted on Indian
society and unfortunately now we all
identify with that yeah now Dowry this
word Dowry you know that's a foreign
word
we always had this custom this tradition
that when a girl becomes gets married
her parents give gifts to her so that
she can kick-start a new life what's
wrong with that all parents love their
children all parents love their
daughters when their daughter
traditionally when a daughter gets
married she goes and becomes part of a
different household right that's how it
it's always been traditionally
so and and the boy she's marrying the
guy the young man she's marrying also is
starting a new life you know we had
these four ashrams these four divisions
in life
um
brahmacharya ashram then
I forget the names I apologize but you
know what it is right
so when you enter the second phase of
Life the second 25 year phase of life
when you uh live a family life and all
that
parents typically give gifts to their
children and mostly to the daughter
because she's going to a different
household so it's been a customer
tradition in India for thousands of
years but it's never been something that
you demand and you expect that I want 73
refrigerators and three color TVs and 24
cars and five kilos of gold that
nonsense is way more recent
in there I think that that is something
that's emerged in the past thousand
years of India's history the Millennium
of humiliation when Society was totally
uh Under Siege
and it could no longer function the way
it had evolved for thousands of years so
I think some of these deficiencies and
defects crept into Indian Society in the
past thousand years to truly understand
Indian Society we have to look at how it
was before the foreign occupation of
India but we don't have any records so
that's the conundrum that we face
so uh so to wrap this up it's always
been an Indian custom to give gifts
to one's daughter when she goes to a
different household there's nothing
wrong with it what's wrong with it it's
a wonderful thing there was also the
concept of srihana that's a whole
different thing but yeah it's connected
to this
so it's an Indian custom but it's not
never been a social evil how the way
it's become in recent times
um I'm not saying it's it's everywhere
you know
but some people had this unfortunate
tendency to demand certain things from
the family of the girl who is a who
you've arranged to marry your son that's
that's unfortunate and that's not how it
should be
okay
Ashish says what do I think about Osho I
think OSHA was a very interesting person
very interesting person I'm not really
read his writings and all that I'm not
really researching him in deep in in
depth
but I think it was a very interesting
person I think he was very sharp
obviously there are lots of controverses
associated with him there was this lady
called Sila
who yeah she's also very interesting
uh she she had this podcast with my
friend anvir so that's the that's
interesting that was interesting yeah so
he was a very interesting person I think
he was very intelligent very sharp I'm
not sure if he had spiritual mystical
Etc powers or not I don't know about
that maybe I mean maybe maybe not I
don't know so I don't know much about
Osho I think he was definitely a
fascinating individual
and uh yeah overall I think his
contribution to the world may have been
more positive in the overall possibly
yeah
okay so I think we are here now at the
end I will take one more question
okay
one more question
uh
and uh well what questions shall I take
saurabh says is Greek older than Tamil
definitely not
no way
Greek is not older than Tamil uh I think
Tamil could
could possibly be as old as good
possibly yeah we don't know the origins
of our languages that's the problem so
we don't have answers but clearly Greek
is not older than Tamil Greek is the
Greek language is something that emerged
from older languages about 3000 years
ago three thousand years ago maximum
Tamil goes way before that so absolutely
not Greek is not older than Tamil and
with that we are at the end of today's
live stream today's Oscar widget session
as always I think there's a whole
different energy when we take questions
from the live chat in the past I've done
so many live streams in which I have
pre-selected questions that also is fun
but I think this is more interactive I
think this is obviously I have more than
a thousand people watching and they're
all asking questions so unfortunately I
cannot answer everybody's questions so I
apologize to those of you who have asked
questions maybe repeatedly and have not
been able to pick them I apologize but
uh we'll keep doing this and hopefully
everybody gets to gets to interact with
me in this manner yeah so thank you very
much all of you I always appreciate this
privilege that I have of being able to
interact with you all in this manner I
really appreciate that so thank you for
watching and I will see you very soon in
the next live stream until then take
care and always remember this keep
raising your standards thank you see you
soon bye